[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "question": "Question 1:",
        "name": "Which of the following characteristics is NOT typically associated with a Decision Support System (DSS)?",
        "options": [
            "Automated data collection and processing",
            "Making strategic planning decisions (DS)",
            "Generate comprehensive reports",
            "Identify factors relevant to decisions"
        ],
        "answer": "Automated data collection and processing",
        "reason": "***"
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "question": "Question 2:",
        "name": "Which of the following is NOT one of the six components of an information system?",
        "options": [
            "Software",
            "Regulator",
            "Processes",
            "People"
        ],
        "answer": "Regulator",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "question": "Question 3:",
        "name": "Which of the following is a qualitative data source?",
        "options": [
            "Loan repayment data from loan system",
            "App usage data from mobile app system",
            "Interview data from a focus group",
            "Bank deposit data from core banking"
        ],
        "answer": "Interview data from a focus group",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "question": "Question 4:",
        "name": "In Power BI Desktop, which feature should you use to combine data from multiple tables based on a related column?",
        "options": [
            "Relationship Builder",
            "DirectQuery",
            "Merge Queries",
            "Conditional Formatting"
        ],
        "answer": "Merge Queries",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "question": "Question 5:",
        "name": "You are analyzing sales data in Power BI and need to calculate the average sales per item sold, which should adjust dynamically based on report filters. Should you create a new measure or a new column, and what would be the correct DAX expression?",
        "options": [
            "A new measure using the CALCULATE function.",
            "A new column directly in the source data file.",
            "A new column using a DAX formula in the data table.",
            "A new measure using SUM and a variable for the tax rate."
        ],
        "answer": "A new measure using the CALCULATE function.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "question": "Question 6:",
        "name": "What is the primary purpose of the DAX language in Power BI?",
        "options": [
            "To manage and configure data refresh schedules",
            "To build a data warehouse to store summarized data",
            "To perform advanced calculations and build visualizations",
            "To import and export data from different sources into Power BI"
        ],
        "answer": "To perform advanced calculations and build visualizations",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "question": "Question 7:",
        "name": "What does the ‘Single’ cross filter direction in Power BI relationships do?",
        "options": [
            "It allows filtering to flow from the primary to the related table, but not the other way around.",
            "It allows filtering to flow from both tables to one another.",
            "It duplicates the filtering effect, applying it twice for emphasis.",
            "It prevents any filtering between related tables."
        ],
        "answer": "It allows filtering to flow from the primary to the related table, but not the other way around.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "question": "Question 8:",
        "name": "Which DAX function in Power BI is best suited for creating a calculated column that classifies rows based on logic, such as categorizing sales amounts into ‘High’, ‘Medium’, and ‘Low’?",
        "options": [
            "CALCULATE()",
            "RANKX()",
            "IF()",
            "UNION()"
        ],
        "answer": "IF()",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "question": "Question 9:",
        "name": "According to Bertin, how does the use of color function in graphical representations?",
        "options": [
            "As a replacement for all other visual variables like size, shape, and position.",
            "As the only means to differentiate between data categories for all types of visualizations.",
            "To enhance the aesthetic appeal of graphs without impacting the viewer’s understanding.",
            "As one of several visual variables that can be used to encode or distinguish information, particularly categorical data."
        ],
        "answer": "As one of several visual variables that can be used to encode or distinguish information, particularly categorical data.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "question": "Question 10:",
        "name": "Which view in Power BI Desktop allows you to categorize a field?",
        "options": [
            "Power Query View",
            "Model View",
            "Data View",
            "Report View"
        ],
        "answer": "Data View",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "question": "Question 11:",
        "name": "For a university, which of the following is NOT business data by definition?",
        "options": [
            "Registration data",
            "Student information",
            "Student social network data",
            "Equipment procurement data"
        ],
        "answer": "Student social network data",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "question": "Question 12:",
        "name": "Which of the following is NOT one of the main activities of MIS?",
        "options": [
            "Corporate Identity design",
            "Data collection and processing",
            "Decision-making support",
            "Performance tracking"
        ],
        "answer": "Corporate Identity design",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "question": "Question 13:",
        "name": "For a marketing team, which of the following questions is the least suitable to answer with business intelligence methods?",
        "options": [
            "Which user segment purchased products the most in the previous year?",
            "What is the current average revenue per user?",
            "What are the probabilities of purchase of each user for each product?",
            "What are the proportions of age groups among company customers?"
        ],
        "answer": "What is the current average revenue per user?",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "question": "Question 14:",
        "name": "What can you use to share reports with other users in Power BI?",
        "options": [
            "Power Query",
            "Power BI Desktop",
            "Power BI Service",
            "Microsoft Word"
        ],
        "answer": "Power BI Service",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "question": "Question 15:",
        "name": "Which of the following is a direct benefit of Business Intelligence?",
        "options": [
            "Reduce cost of operations",
            "Digital transformation of the business process",
            "Detect dirty data",
            "Make decisions from insight"
        ],
        "answer": "Make decisions from insight",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "question": "Question 16:",
        "name": "In the context of business intelligence and analytics, Power BI Desktop is best described as a tool for:",
        "options": [
            "Development of web platforms",
            "Creation, integration, and sharing of interactive data visualizations",
            "Editing multimedia content for presentations",
            "Managing and manipulating textual datasets"
        ],
        "answer": "Creation, integration, and sharing of interactive data visualizations",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "question": "Question 17:",
        "name": "What characterizes the global level of reading, as defined by Jacques Bertin, in the context of graphic interpretation?",
        "options": [
            "Memorizing every data point and detail for later recall",
            "Understanding the broad themes and messages conveyed by the entire graphic",
            "Focusing on minor discrepancies and outliers within the data",
            "Showing details of data sources and methodology behind the data collection"
        ],
        "answer": "Understanding the broad themes and messages conveyed by the entire graphic",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "question": "Question 18:",
        "name": "For a hospital, which of the following is a secondary data source?",
        "options": [
            "COVID ATK test result",
            "CT scan of a patient",
            "Patient interview by doctor",
            "Diagnosis instructions by WHO"
        ],
        "answer": "Diagnosis instructions by WHO",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "question": "Question 19:",
        "name": "In Power BI Desktop, when needing to analyze the operational cash flow of a company (i.e., company receiving and paying money), starting with the opening balance and ending with the closing balance for each period, while highlighting increases, decreases, and net changes, which chart type provides the most insightful visualization?",
        "options": [
            "Line and Clustered Column Chart",
            "Scatter Chart with a Play Axis",
            "Bar Chart",
            "Waterfall Chart"
        ],
        "answer": "Waterfall Chart",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "question": "Question 20:",
        "name": "You are creating a Power BI report for your university’s alumni relations team to categorize alumni into levels of engagement (High, Medium, Low) based on their total donations and event attendance. This categorization is based on historical data and will be used for various reports. Considering the need for fixed categories based on past activities, should you:",
        "options": [
            "Create a new measure to rank alumni based on their engagement compared to others",
            "Create a new measure to dynamically calculate each alumnus’s engagement score",
            "Use DirectQuery to link to an external database that calculates engagement levels",
            "Create a new column in the alumni data table to assign a static engagement level"
        ],
        "answer": "Create a new column in the alumni data table to assign a static engagement level",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "question": "Question 21:",
        "name": "What is the final output of business intelligence?",
        "options": [
            "Decision",
            "Software",
            "Model",
            "Data"
        ],
        "answer": "Decision",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "question": "Question 22:",
        "name": "The university research team needs to analyze student data including study hours, GPA, and extracurricular activities to find trends and help improve student services. They want to use Power BI to find relationships within the complex data. Which Power BI solution should they use to best display their findings?",
        "options": [
            "Use line charts to show changes in GPA over time for different student groups, adding slicers for viewers to select specific demographics.",
            "Create separate pie charts for each type of data (study hours, GPA, activities) and use basic filters to sort by year.",
            "Build a report with a mix of charts: scatter plots for relationships between study hours and GPA, bar charts for activity levels, and use slicers and drill-through for detailed analysis.",
            "Make one large bar chart comparing the average GPA of students involved in different numbers of activities without any interactive elements."
        ],
        "answer": "Build a report with a mix of charts: scatter plots for relationships between study hours and GPA, bar charts for activity levels, and use slicers and drill-through for detailed analysis.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "question": "Question 23:",
        "name": "In Power BI, which of the following DAX functions is used to calculate the total sum of a column in a table?",
        "options": [
            "AVERAGE()",
            "TOTAL()",
            "COUNT()",
            "SUM()"
        ],
        "answer": "SUM()",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "question": "Question 24:",
        "name": "In Power BI using DAX, what function would you use to create a measure that calculates the total sales after applying an initial filter on the ‘Year’ column to show only the sales from 2020?",
        "options": [
            "FILTER(SUM([Sales]), ‘Year’ = 2020)",
            "SUM(Sales, ‘Year’ = 2020)",
            "CALCULATE(SUM([Sales]), ‘Year’ = 2020)",
            "TOTAL_SALES()"
        ],
        "answer": "CALCULATE(SUM([Sales]), ‘Year’ = 2020)",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "question": "Question 25:",
        "name": "Which of the following is NOT one of BI capabilities?",
        "options": [
            "Operational efficiency",
            "Organizational memory",
            "Insights and decisions",
            "Information integration"
        ],
        "answer": "Operational efficiency",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "question": "Question 26:",
        "name": "Which of the following is NOT a factor that drives the adoption of business intelligence?",
        "options": [
            "Computer technology has become more expensive, so making any decision must be more precise.",
            "The organization needs a competitive advantage to compete with other companies that may utilize their data in competition.",
            "The organization has an ability to accumulate large and varied data related to business processes.",
            "The organization requires making fast and complex decisions that involve multiple parties and processes."
        ],
        "answer": "Computer technology has become more expensive, so making any decision must be more precise.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "question": "Question 27:",
        "name": "For a commercial bank, which of the following is an external data source?",
        "options": [
            "Government inflation data",
            "Money transfer data",
            "Loan collateral data",
            "Deposit account data"
        ],
        "answer": "Government inflation data",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "question": "Question 28:",
        "name": "The admissions department of a university wants to analyze application trends over the last five years to better understand peak application times and the demographic breakdown of applicants. Using Power BI, which type of chart should they primarily use to visualize monthly application trends over this period?",
        "options": [
            "Funnel Chart",
            "Line Chart",
            "TreeMap",
            "Pie Chart"
        ],
        "answer": "Line Chart",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "question": "Question 29:",
        "name": "Which of the following scenarios is best suited for using DirectQuery mode in Power BI?",
        "options": [
            "When you need to analyze large datasets that exceed Power BI’s data capacity limits.",
            "When the highest performance of report visuals is the top priority without considering data size.",
            "When real-time data updates are not necessary, and data volume is moderate.",
            "When working with small, static datasets that do not change."
        ],
        "answer": "When you need to analyze large datasets that exceed Power BI’s data capacity limits.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "question": "Question 30:",
        "name": "What is the preferred method for encoding nominal data to facilitate comparison and differentiation?",
        "options": [
            "Gradient of color",
            "Texture variation",
            "Shape differentiation",
            "Size variation"
        ],
        "answer": "Shape differentiation",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "question": "Question 31:",
        "name": "Which of the following tasks is NOT related to business intelligence?",
        "options": [
            "Data workflow implementation",
            "Business requirement analysis",
            "Data visualization",
            "Data analysis and modeling"
        ],
        "answer": "Data workflow implementation",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "question": "Question 32:",
        "name": "Which of the following tasks is the LEAST related to the business intelligence workflow by definition?",
        "options": [
            "Analyze the problem",
            "Deploy the model",
            "Interact with the data",
            "Share your result"
        ],
        "answer": "Deploy the model",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "question": "Question 33:",
        "name": "In Power BI, what is the main difference between Import and DirectQuery modes when connecting to a data source?",
        "options": [
            "Import mode copies the data into Power BI, while DirectQuery mode maintains a live connection to the data source.",
            "Import and DirectQuery modes both maintain a live connection, but DirectQuery has faster refresh rates.",
            "DirectQuery mode copies the data into Power BI, while Import mode maintains a live connection to the data source.",
            "Import and DirectQuery modes both copy data into Power BI but at different refresh rates."
        ],
        "answer": "Import mode copies the data into Power BI, while DirectQuery mode maintains a live connection to the data source.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "question": "Question 34:",
        "name": "Suppose that these people are parts of the business requirement gathering meeting. Which of the following situations DOES NOT demonstrate analytical thinking skills?",
        "options": [
            "Bob asks questions related to the business process.",
            "Dave revises the report and prepares the template for presentation.",
            "Alice summarizes the important issues in the requirement gathering.",
            "Craig uses fishbone analysis and identifies important issues."
        ],
        "answer": "Dave revises the report and prepares the template for presentation.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "question": "Question 35:",
        "name": "Which of the following chart types is NOT supported by Power BI Desktop’s native functionality?",
        "options": [
            "Histograms, showing the distribution of numerical data across predefined bins.",
            "Line Charts, used for displaying data trends and changes over time.",
            "Gantt Charts, showing project management timelines.",
            "Pie Charts, illustrating the proportional makeup of a dataset."
        ],
        "answer": "Gantt Charts, showing project management timelines.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "question": "Question 36:",
        "name": "Among the following software options, which one is the LEAST suitable for classification as a knowledge work system?",
        "options": [
            "PowerPoint for executives to make impactful presentations.",
            "AutoCAD for 3D-printer hobbyists to design objects.",
            "Jupyter Notebook for data scientists to use Python programming.",
            "Illustrator for artists to draw line art."
        ],
        "answer": "PowerPoint for executives to make impactful presentations.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "question": "Question 37:",
        "name": "Which of the following analysis outputs should be done by a data scientist instead of a BI specialist?",
        "options": [
            "KPIs that measure company performance.",
            "Dashboards showing company current statuses.",
            "Reports analyzing issues in operations.",
            "Predictive model that forecasts sales."
        ],
        "answer": "Predictive model that forecasts sales.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "question": "Question 38:",
        "name": "Which of the following is NOT an example of a transaction processing system?",
        "options": [
            "In-app purchase system in mobile phones.",
            "POS sales system at a department store.",
            "Cloud data storage (e.g., Dropbox, Google Drive, etc.).",
            "ATM machine system for cash withdrawals."
        ],
        "answer": "Cloud data storage (e.g., Dropbox, Google Drive, etc.).",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "question": "Question 39:",
        "name": "Regarding data import into Power BI Desktop, which statement most accurately reflects its capabilities?",
        "options": [
            "It offers a broad range of data connectivity options, including files, databases, and cloud services, facilitating a comprehensive data analysis experience.",
            "It focuses data import exclusively on live database connections, disregarding other data sources.",
            "It limits data integration to text-based transfers from word processing documents.",
            "It supports data entry solely through manual input interfaces within the platform."
        ],
        "answer": "It offers a broad range of data connectivity options, including files, databases, and cloud services, facilitating a comprehensive data analysis experience.",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "question": "Question 40:",
        "name": "How can you use DAX in Power BI to apply an initial filter that excludes products from the “Electronics” category while calculating total revenue?",
        "options": [
            "SUMX(EXCLUDE('Products', (Category) = \"Electronics\"), (Revenue))",
            "REMOVEFILTERS((Revenue), (Category) = \"Electronics\")",
            "CALCULATE(SUM(Revenue), NOT((Category) = \"Electronics\"))",
            "CALCULATE(SUM(Revenue), (Category) <> \"Electronics\")"
        ],
        "answer": "CALCULATE(SUM(Revenue), NOT((Category) = \"Electronics\"))",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "question": "Question 41:",
        "name": "What is the primary function of Power Query Editor in Power BI Desktop?",
        "options": [
            "Directing the operational timing and logistics of data refresh and synchronization tasks",
            "Enabling data manipulation, including transformation, cleaning, and integration before analysis",
            "Implementing and managing user access levels and data security measures",
            "Executing complex database administrative operations exclusively"
        ],
        "answer": "Enabling data manipulation, including transformation, cleaning, and integration before analysis",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "question": "Question 42:",
        "name": "Which functionality in Power BI Desktop is the most suitable for performing data cleaning?",
        "options": [
            "Power Query Editor",
            "Data View",
            "Model View",
            "Report View"
        ],
        "answer": "Power Query Editor",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "question": "Question 43:",
        "name": "According to Jacques Bertin’s theory, what does the elementary level of reading a graphic representation involve?",
        "options": [
            "Analyzing the graphic’s background and design elements",
            "Understanding the overall trend or message of the graphic at first glance",
            "Comparing and contrasting different sections of the graphic",
            "Identifying and interpreting individual data points or symbols"
        ],
        "answer": "Identifying and interpreting individual data points or symbols",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "question": "Question 44:",
        "name": "Which of the following is an office automation system?",
        "options": [
            "Bank transfer in mobile app",
            "Accounting system",
            "Queue management system",
            "Executive data dashboard"
        ],
        "answer": "Accounting system",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "question": "Question 45:",
        "name": "For a detailed comparison of sales performance across different product categories, where each category’s contribution to total sales needs to be assessed at a specific point in time, which additional Power BI Desktop visualization offers the most clarity when a line chart already shows sales per point in time?",
        "options": [
            "100% Stacked column chart",
            "Pie chart",
            "Multi-row card",
            "Radar chart"
        ],
        "answer": "100% Stacked column chart",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "question": "Question 46:",
        "name": "As a Marketing Data Analyst analyzing customer behavior and campaign performance in Power BI Desktop, which of the following steps is appropriate for integrating sales and marketing data and analyzing different marketing campaigns’ effectiveness?",
        "options": [
            "Import unrelated financial data and use a scatter plot to represent marketing spend versus sales",
            "Use DirectQuery to connect to live social media data only and visualize data using a map",
            "Import only sales data from the last month and use a pie chart to show different products sold",
            "Combine sales and marketing data from various sources, establish relationships, and use a line chart to compare monthly sales conversion rates of different campaigns"
        ],
        "answer": "Combine sales and marketing data from various sources, establish relationships, and use a line chart to compare monthly sales conversion rates of different campaigns",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "question": "Question 47:",
        "name": "When analyzing financial time series data in Power BI Desktop, which visualization should be used to display cumulative trends and seasonal effects, particularly for showcasing quarterly revenue growth over several years?",
        "options": [
            "Line chart",
            "Stacked bar chart",
            "Area chart",
            "Clustered column chart"
        ],
        "answer": "Area chart",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "question": "Question 48:",
        "name": "What is the purpose of the Data Model in Power BI Desktop?",
        "options": [
            "To create and manage relationships between different data tables",
            "To store passwords and user information",
            "To change the color and design of the reports",
            "To schedule the report publishing times"
        ],
        "answer": "To create and manage relationships between different data tables",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "question": "Question 49:",
        "name": "In Bertin’s theory, what is the significance of the concept of ‘retinal variables’ in the design of information graphics?",
        "options": [
            "They refer to properties that can be perceived by the human eye, used to encode quantitative and qualitative data",
            "They are variables that should be avoided as they cause strain to the viewer’s eyes",
            "They represent a set of principles for designing optical illusions",
            "They are irrelevant to modern graphic design and have been disproved by contemporary research"
        ],
        "answer": "They refer to properties that can be perceived by the human eye, used to encode quantitative and qualitative data",
        "reason": ""
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "question": "Question 50:",
        "name": "Company A wants to inspect all of their databases for data quality issues and make corrections to any mistakes. Which role is the most suitable for this task?",
        "options": [
            "Business Intelligence specialist",
            "Business analyst",
            "Data engineer",
            "Data scientist"
        ],
        "answer": "Data engineer",
        "reason": ""
    }
]